ⓘ These English & Foreign subtitles created by ZoowlCZ (ver. 2025-08) are an expanded version of the English subtitles (6053820) uploaded by lusiads to OpenSubtitles.
ⓘ Very special thanks to Gwaith-i-Phethdain, Magpie of A Magpie's Nest and Friends, and Monoverantus
for their extraordinary work on deciphering the dialogs and lyrics.
ⓘ Special thanks also to TheGloriousLori and José Figueredo.
ⓘ For correct displaying of these subtitles, use a media player
supporting ASS tags in .srt files.
[Sindarin] ♫ Man ammen toltha i dann hen morn? ♫
[English] ♫ Who brings to us this token of darkness? ♫
[Sindarin] I amar prestar aen.
The world is changed.
[Sindarin] Han mathon ne nen.
[Sindarin] ♫ Si dannatha, nauva. ♫
[English] ♫ Will now fall, will be. ♫
I feel it in the water.
[Sindarin] Han mathon ne chae.
I feel it in the earth.
[Sindarin] A han noston ned 'wilith.
I smell it in the air.
Much that once was...
...is lost.
For none now live who remember it.
The Lord of the Rings.
It began with the forging of the great rings.
Three were given to the elves:
Immortal, wisest and fairest of all beings.
Seven to the dwarf-lords:
Great miners and craftsmen of the mountain halls.
And nine...
...nine rings were gifted to the race of men...
...who, above all else, desire power.
For within these rings was bound
the strength and will to govern each race.
But they were all of them deceived.
For another ring was made.
In the land of Mordor,
in the fires of Mount Doom...
... the Dark Lord Sauron forged
in secret a master ring...
... to control all others.
And into this ring he poured
his cruelty, his malice...
...and his will to dominate all life.
One ring to rule them all.
One by one...
... the free lands of Middle-earth
fell to the power of the ring.
But there were some who resisted.
A last alliance of men and elves
marched against the armies of Mordor.
And on the slopes of Mount Doom, they
fought for the freedom of Middle-earth.
[Adûnaic] ♫ Nênâkham nêpâm... ♫
[English] ♫ We approach, we grasp... ♫
[Adûnaic] ♫ ...abâr-at... ♫
[English] ♫ ...power and... ♫
[Sindarin] Tangado haid!
[English] Hold positions!
[Adûnaic] ♫ ...aglar. ♫
[English] ♫ ...glory. ♫
[Sindarin] Leithio i philinn!
[English] Release the arrows!
[Adûnaic] ♫ Nêtabdam dâurad. ♫
[English] ♫ We cling to the darkness. ♫
[Adûnaic] ♫ Nidir nêpâm. ♫
[English] ♫ The Nine, we grasp. ♫
[Adûnaic] ♫ Nêpâm nêd... ♫
[English] ♫ We grasp for ourselves... ♫
[Adûnaic] ♫ ...aglar. ♫
[English] ♫ ...glory. ♫
Victory was near.
But the power of the ring...
...could not be undone.
[Adûnaic] ♫ Nênâkham nêpâm... ♫
[English] ♫ We approach, we grasp... ♫
[Adûnaic] ♫ ...abâr-at... ♫
[English] ♫ ...power and... ♫
[Adûnaic] ♫ ...aglar. ♫
[English] ♫ ...glory. ♫
It was in this moment...
... when all hope had faded...
... that Isildur, son of the king,
took up his father's sword.
Sauron, the enemy of the free peoples
of Middle-earth, was defeated.
The ring passed to Isildur...
... who had this one chance to destroy evil forever.
But the hearts of men...
...are easily corrupted.
And the ring of power has a will of its own.
It betrayed Isildur...
... to his death.
And some things
that should not have been forgotten...
...were lost.
History became legend...
...legend became myth.
And for two and a half thousand years...
... the ring passed out of all knowledge.
Until, when chance came...
...it ensnared a new bearer.
My precious.
The ring came to the creature Gollum...
... who took it deep into the tunnels
of the Misty Mountains.
And there it consumed him.
It came to me.
My own. My love. My own.
My precious.
The ring brought to Gollum unnatural long life.
For 500 years it poisoned his mind.
And in the gloom of Gollum's cave, it waited.
Darkness crept back into the forests of the world.
Rumor grew of a shadow in the East...
... whispers of a nameless fear.
And the ring of power perceived...
...its time had now come.
It abandoned Gollum.
But something happened then
the ring did not intend.
It was picked up by the most
unlikely creature imaginable.
What's this?
A hobbit.
Bilbo Baggins of the Shire.
A ring.
Lost!
My precious is lost!
For the time will soon come...
... when Hobbits will shape the fortunes of all.
The 22nd day of September...
...in the year 1400...
...by Shire-reckoning.
Bag End, Bagshot Row.
Hobbiton, Westfarthing...
...the Shire...
...Middle-earth.
The third age of this world.
The Fellowship of the Ring.
There and back again.
A Hobbit's tale.
By Bilbo Baggins.
Now...
...where to begin?
Ah, yes....
"Concerning...
...Hobbits."
Hobbits have been living and farming
in the four Farthings of the Shire...
...for many hundreds of years...
...quite content to ignore and be ignored...
...by the world of the big folk.
Middle-earth being, after all,
full of strange creatures beyond count...
...Hobbits must seem of little importance...
...being neither renowned as great warriors...
...nor counted among the very wise.
Frodo! Someone at the door.
In fact, it has been remarked by some...
... that Hobbits' only real passion is for food.
A rather unfair observation...
...as we have also developed a keen
interest in the brewing of ales...
...and the smoking of pipe-weed.
But where our hearts truly lie...
...is in peace and quiet...
...and good, tilled earth.
For all Hobbits share a love of things that grow.
And yes, no doubt to others our ways seem quaint.
But today of all days.
It is brought home to me...
It is no bad thing to celebrate a simple life.
Frodo, the door!
Sticklebacks. Where is that boy?
Frodo!
Down from the door where it began
And I must follow if I can
The road goes ever on and on
Down from the door where it began
Now far ahead the road has gone
And I must follow if I can
- You're late.
A wizard is never late, Frodo Baggins.
Nor is he early.
He arrives precisely when he means to.
It's wonderful to see you, Gandalf!
You didn't think I'd miss
your Uncle Bilbo's birthday?
How is the old rascal?
I hear it's going to be a party
of special magnificence.
You know Bilbo.
He's got the whole piece in an uproar.
Well, that should please him.
Half the Shire's been invited.
And the rest of them are turning up anyway.
And so life in the Shire goes on...
... very much as it has this past age.
Full of its own comings and goings,
with change coming slowly.
If it comes at all.
For things are made to endure in the Shire...
...passing from one generation to the next.
There's always been a Baggins
living here under the Hill...
...in Bag End.
And there always will be.
To tell you the truth,
Bilbo's been a bit odd lateIy.
I mean, more than usual.
He's taken to locking himself in his study.
He spends hours and hours poring over
old maps when he thinks I'm not looking.
Where's it gone?
He's up to something.
- All right, then. Keep your secrets.
- What?
But I know you have something to do with it.
Good gracious me.
Before you came along, we Bagginses
were very well thought of.
Indeed.
Never had any adventures
or did anything unexpected.
If you're referring to the incident with the dragon.
I was barely involved.
All I did was give your uncle
a little nudge out of the door.
Whatever you did, you've been officially
labeled a disturber of the peace.
Oh, really?
Gandalf! Gandalf!
Fireworks, Gandalf!
- Gandalf!
- Fireworks, Gandalf!
Gandalf?
- I'm glad you're back.
- So am I, dear boy.
So am I.
No, thank you!
We don't want any more visitors,
well-wishers or distant relations!
And what about very old friends?
Gandalf?
- Bilbo Baggins.
- My dear Gandalf!
Good to see you. 111 years old!
Who would believe it?
You haven't aged a day.
Come on, come in!
Welcome, welcome.
Oh, here we are.
Tea...or maybe something a littIe stronger?
I've got a few bottles of the old winyard left - 1296.
Very good year. Almost as old as I am.
It was laid down by my father.
What say we open one, eh?
Just tea, thank you.
I was expecting you sometime last week.
Not that it matters. You come and go as
you please. Always have and always will.
You caught me a bit unprepared I'm afraid.
We've only got cold chicken and a bit of pickle....
There's some cheese here.
No, that won't do.
We've got raspberry jam, an apple tart....
But not much for afters.
Oh, no, we're all right.
I've just found some sponge cake.
I could make you some eggs if you'd li...
- Just tea, thank you.
- Oh, right.
- You don't mind if I eat, do you?
- No, not at all.
Bilbo! Bilbo Baggins!
I'm not at home!
It's the Sackville-Bagginses.
- I know you're in there!
- They're after the house.
They've never forgiven me for living this long.
I've got to get away from these confounded
relatives, hanging on the bell all day...
...never giving me a moment's peace.
I want to see mountains again.
Mountains, Gandalf!
And then find somewhere quiet
where I can finish my book. Oh, tea.
- So you mean to go through with your plan?
- Yes, yes. It's all in hand.
All the arrangements are made.
Oh, thank you.
Frodo suspects something.
Of course he does. He's a Baggins...
...not some blockheaded Bracegirdle
from Hardbottle.
You will tell him, won't you?
- Yes, yes.
- He's very fond of you.
I know.
He'd probably come with me if I asked him.
I think in his heart, Frodo's
still in love with the Shire.
The woods, the fields.
Little rivers.
I am old, Gandalf.
I know I don't look it, but I'm
beginning to feel it in my heart.
I feel thin.
Sort of stretched...
...like butter scraped over too much bread.
I need a holiday. A very Long holiday.
And I don't expect I shall return.
In fact, I mean not to.
Old Toby.
The finest weed in the Southfarthing.
Gandalf, my old friend...
...this will be a night to remember.
Hello, hello.
Fatty Bolger. Lovely to see you.
Welcome, welcome.
Go on, Sam. Ask Rosie for a dance.
- I think I'll just have another ale.
- Oh, no, you don't.
Go on!
So there I was...
...at the mercy of three monstrous trolls.
And they were all arguing amongst themselves...
...about how they were going to cook us.
Whether it be turned on a spit, or to sit
on us one by one, squash us into jelly.
They spent so much time arguing
the whithertos and the whyfors...
...that the sun's first light
crept over the top of the trees...
...and turned them all to stone!
Quickly.
Up they go!
No no, the big one - big one
Mrs. Bracegirdle, how nice to see you.
Welcome, welcome.
Are all these children yours?
Good gracious, you have been productive.
Bilbo?
Sackville-Bagginses!
Quickly, hide!
Thank you, my boy.
You're a good lad, Frodo.
I'm very selfish, you know.
Yes, I am. Very selfish.
I don't know why I took you in after
your mother and father died...
...but it wasn't out of charity.
I think it was because...
...of all my numerous relations...
...you were the one Baggins that showed real spirit.
Bilbo, have you been at the Gaffer's home brew?
No.
Well, yes, but that's not the point.
The point is, Frodo...
...you'll be all right.
- Done!
- You're supposed to stick it in the ground.
- It is in the ground.
- Outside!
This was your idea.
Bilbo.
Bilbo, watch out for the dragon!
Nonsense. There hasn't been a dragon
in these parts for thousands of years.
- That was good.
- Let's get another one.
Meriadoc Brandybuck and Peregrin Took.
I might've known.
Speech, Bilbo!
Speech!
My dear Bagginses and Boffins...
...Tooks and Brandybucks...
...Grubbs, Chubbs...
...Hornblowers...
...Bolgers...
...Bracegirdles...
...and Proudfoots.
- Proudfeet!
Today is my 111th birthday!
Happy birthday!
But alas, eleventy-one years is
far too short a time to live among...
...such excellent and admirable Hobbits.
I don't know half of you
half as well as I should like...
...and I like less than half of you
half as well as you deserve.
I have things to do.
I've put this off for far too long.
I regret to announce this is the end!
I'm going now.
I bid you all a very fond farewell.
Goodbye.
I suppose you think that was terribly clever.
Come on, Gandalf.
Did you see their faces?
There are many magic rings in
this world, Bilbo Baggins...
...and none of them should be used lightly.
It was just a bit of fun.
Oh, you're probably right, as usual.
- You will keep an eye on Frodo, won't you?
- Two eyes.
As often as I can spare them.
- I'm leaving everything to him.
- What about this ring of yours?
- Is that staying too?
- Yes, yes.
It's in an envelope over there on the mantelpiece.
No. Wait, it's...
...here in my pocket.
Isn't that--? Isn't that odd, now?
Yet, after all, why not?
- Why shouldn t I keep it?
- I think you should leave the ring behind.
Is that so hard?
Well, no.
And yes.
Now it comes to it,
I don't feel l ike parting with it.
It's mine. I found it! It came to me!
- There's no need to get angry.
- Well, if I'm angry, it's your fault!
It's mine.
My own.
- My precious.
- Precious?
It's been called that before, but not by you.
What business is it of yours
what I do with my own things?
I think you've had that ring quite long enough.
- You want it for yourself!
- Bilbo Baggins!
Do not take me for some conjurer of cheap tricks.
I am not trying to rob you.
I'm trying to help you.
All your long years, we've been friends.
Trust me as you once did.
Let it go.
You're right, Gandalf.
The ring must go to Frodo.
It's late. The road is long.
Yes, it is time.
Bilbo, the ring is still in your pocket.
I've thought up an ending for my book:
"And he lived happily ever after
to the end of his days."
And I'm sure you will, my dear friend.
Goodbye, Gandalf.
Goodbye, dear Bilbo.
The road goes ever on and on...
Until our next meeting.
It's mine. My own.
My precious.
Riddles in the dark.
Bilbo!
My precious.
Precious.
He's gone, hasn't he?
He talked for so long about leaving...
...I didn't think he'd really do it.
Gandalf?
Bilbo's ring.
He's gone to stay with the elves.
He's left you Bag End.
Along with all his possessions.
The ring is yours now.
- Put it somewhere out of sight.
- Where are you going?
- There are some things that I must see to.
- What things?
- Questions. Questions that need answering.
- You've only just arrived.
I don't understand.
Neither do I.
Keep it secret.
Keep it safe.
Shire!
Baggins!
[Adûnaic] ♫ Nêbâbîtham Magânanê. ♫
[English] ♫ We renounce our Creator. ♫
"The year 3434 of the second age.
Here follows the account of Isildur,
High King of Gondor...
...and the finding of the ring of power."
"It has come to me.
The one ring.
It shall be an heirloom of my kingdom.
All those who follow in my bloodline
shall be bound to its fate...
...for I will risk no hurt to the ring.
It is precious to me...
...though I buy it with great pain.
The markings upon the band begin to fade.
The writing, which at first was as clear
as red flame, has all but disappeared.
A secret now that only fire can tell."
Shire...
...Baggins.
There's no Bagginses around here.
They're all up in Hobbiton.
That way.
"Hey ho to the dock I go
To heal my heart and drown my woe
Rain may fall and wind may blow
But there still be...
...many miles to go
Sweet is the sound of the pouring rain
And the stream that falls from hill to plain
Better than rain or rippling brook
Is a mug of beer inside this Took!"
There's been some strange folk crossing the Shire.
Dwarves and others of a less than savory nature.
War is brewing.
The mountains are fair teeming with goblins.
Far-off tales and children s stories, that's all that is.
You're beginning to sound like that old
Bilbo Baggins. Cracked, he was.
Young Mr. Frodo here, he's cracking.
And proud of it.
- Cheers, Gaffer.
- Aye. Cheers.
Weel it's none of our concern what
goes on beyond our borders.
Keep your nose out of trouble,
and no trouble'll come to you.
- Good night, lads.
- Good night.
Good night, sweet maiden of the golden ale.
Mind who you're sweet-taking.
Don't worry, Sam.
Rosie knows an idiot when she sees one.
Does she?
- Good night, Sam.
- Good night, Mr. Frodo.
Is it secret? Is it safe?
What are you doing?
Hold out your hand, Frodo.
It's quite cool.
What can you see?
Can you see anything?
Nothing.
There's nothing.
Wait.
There are markings.
It's some form of Elvish.
I can't read it.
There are few who can.
The language is that of Mordor,
which I will not utter here.
Mordor!
In the common tongue, it says:
"One ring to rule them all...
...One ring to find them...
...One ring to bring them all...
...and in the darkness bind them."
This is the One ring...
...forged by the Dark Lord Sauron
in the fires of Mount Doom.
Taken by Isildur from the hand of Sauron himself.
Bilbo found it.
- In Gollum's cave.
- Yes.
For 60 years, the ring lay quiet in Bilbo's keeping...
...prolonging his life, delaying old age.
But no longer, Frodo.
Evil is stirring in Mordor.
The ring has awoken.
It's heard its master's call.
But he was destroyed.
Sauron was destroyed.
No, Frodo.
The spirit of Sauron endured.
His life force is bound to the ring,
and the ring survived.
Sauron has returned.
His orcs have multiplied.
His fortress at Barad-dûr
is rebuilt in the land of Mordor.
Sauron needs only this ring to cover
all the lands in a second darkness.
He is seeking it.
Seeking it - All his thought is bent on it.
For the ring yearns above all else...
...to return to the hand of its master.
They are one...
...the ring and the Dark Lord.
Frodo...
...he must never find it.
All right.
We put it away. We keep it hidden.
We never speak of it again.
No one knows it's here, do they?
Do they, Gandalf?
There is one other who knew
that Bilbo had the ring.
I looked everywhere for the creature Gollum.
But the enemy found him first.
I don't know how long they tortured him.
But amidst the endless screams and
inane babble, they discerned two words:
Shire!
Baggins!
Shire.
Baggins.
But that would lead them here!
Who goes there?
Take it, Gandalf!
- Take it!
- No, Frodo.
- You must take it!
- You cannot offer me this ring!
- I'm giving it to you!
- Don't tempt me, Frodo!
I dare not take it.
Not even to keep it safe.
Understand, Frodo...
...I would use this ring from a desire to do good.
But through me, it would wield a power
too great and terrible to imagine.
- But it cannot stay in the Shire!
- No.
No, it can't.
What must I do?
- You must leave. And leave quickly.
- Where? Where do I go?
Get out of the Shire.
Make for the village of Bree.
Bree.
- What about you?
- I'll be waiting for you...
...at the inn of the Prancing Pony.
- And the ring will be safe there?
- I don't know, Frodo.
I don't have any answers.
I must see the head of my order.
He is both wise and powerful. Trust me, Frodo.
He'll know what to do.
You'll have to leave the name
of Baggins behind you.
That name is not safe outside the Shire.
Travel only by day.
And stay off the road.
I can cut across country easily enough.
My dear Frodo.
Hobbits really are amazing creatures.
You can learn all that there is to
know about their ways in a month.
And yet, after a hundred years...
...they can still surprise you.
Get down.
Confound it all, Samwise Gamgee!
Have you been eavesdropping?
I haven't been dropping no eaves. Honest.
I was just cutting the grass under
the window there...If you follow me.
A little late for trimming the verge, don't you think?
- I heard raised voices.
- What did you hear? Speak!
Nothing important.
That is, I heard a good deal
about a ring, and a Dark Lord...
...and something about the end of the world but...
Please, Mr. Gandalf, sir, don't hurt me.
Don't turn me into anything unnatural.
No?
Perhaps not.
I've thought of a better use for you.
Come along, Samwise. Keep up.
Be careful, both of you.
The enemy has many spies in his service:
Birds, beasts.
Is it safe?
Never put it on...
...for the agents of the Dark Lord
will be drawn to its power.
Always remember, Frodo...
...the ring is trying to get back to its master.
It wants to be found.
This is it.
This is what?
If I take one more step...
...it'll be the farthest away
from home I've ever been.
Come on, Sam.
Remember what Bilbo used to say:
- "It's a dangerous business, Frodo."
- "Going out your door.
You step onto the road,
and if you don't keep your feet...
... there's no knowing where
you might be swept off to."
[Sindarin] ♫ Rîn athar annún-aearath ... ♫
[English] ♫ O Queen beyond the Western Seas... ♫
Sam.
[Sindarin] ♫ ... calad ammen ... ♫
[English] ♫ ... light to us ... ♫
Wood-elves.
[Sindarin] ♫ ... i reniar ... ♫
[English] ♫ ... who wander ... ♫
[Sindarin] ♫ ... mi 'aladhremmin Ennorath. ♫
[English] ♫ ... amid the tree-woven lands of Middle-earth. ♫
They're going to the harbor
beyond the White Towers.
[Sindarin] ♫ A Elbereth Gilthoniel ... ♫
[English] ♫ O Elbereth Star-kindler ... ♫
To the Grey Havens.
They're leaving Middle-earth.
Never to return.
[Sindarin] ♫ ... i chin a thûl lín míriel. ♫
[English] ♫ ... your eyes and breath shining like jewels. ♫
I don't know why...
...it makes me sad.
Everywhere I lie there's a dirty
great root sticking into my back.
Just shut your eyes...
...and imagine you're back in your own bed...
...with a soft mattress and a lovely feather pillow.
It's not working, Mr. Frodo.
I'm never going to be able to sleep out here.
Me neither, Sam.
Smoke rises from the Mountain of Doom.
The hour grows late.
And Gandalf the Grey rides to Isengard...
...seeking my counsel.
For that is why you have come, is it not?
My old friend.
Saruman.
- You are sure of this?
- Beyond any doubt.
So the ring of power has been found.
All these long years, it was in the Shire.
- Under my very nose.
- Yet you did not have the wit to see it.
Your love of the halfling's leaf
has clearly slowed your mind.
But we still have time.
Time enough to counter Sauron if we act quickly.
Time?
What time do you think we have?
Sauron has regained much of his former strength.
He cannot yet take physical form...
...but his spirit has lost none of its potency.
Concealed within his fortress,
the Lord of Mordor sees all.
His gaze pierces cloud, shadow, earth and flesh.
You know of what I speak, Gandalf.
A great eye, lidless, wreathed in flame.
The eye of Sauron.
He is gathering all evil to him.
Very soon, he'll have summoned an army...
...great enough for an assault upon Middle-earth.
You know this?
How?
I have seen it.
A palantir is a dangerous tool, Saruman.
Why?
Why should we fear to use it?
They are not all accounted for,
the lost seeing-stones.
We do not know who else may be watching.
The hour is later than you think.
Sauron's forces are already moving.
The Nine have left Minas Morgul.
The Nine?
They crossed the river Isen on Midsummer's Eve...
...disguised as riders in black.
- They've reached the Shire?
- They will find the ring.
And kill the one who carries it.
Frodo!
You did not seriously think that a hobbit
could contend with the will of Sauron?
There are none who can.
Against the power of Mordor...
...there can be no victory.
We must join with him, Gandalf.
We must join with Sauron.
It would be wise, my friend.
Tell me...
...friend...
...when did Saruman the Wise abandon reason for madness?
I gave you the chance of...
...aiding me willingly...
...but you have elected the way of pain!
Mr. Frodo?
Frodo? Frodo!
- I thought I'd lost you.
- What are you taking about?
- It's just something Gandalf said.
- What did he say?
"Don't you lose him, Samwise Gamgee."
And I don't mean to.
Sam, we're still in the Shire.
What could possibly happen?
Frodo.
- Merry, it's Frodo Baggins.
- Hello, Frodo.
Get off him.
Come on, Frodo.
What's the meaning of this?
You've been into Farmer Maggot's crop!
You get back here!
Get out of my field!
You'll know the devil if I catch up with you!
I don't know why he's so upset.
It's only a couple of carrots.
And some cabbages.
And those three bags of potatoes
that we lifted last week.
- And then the mushrooms the week before.
- Yes, Pippin. My point is...
...he's clearly overreacting.
Run!
Oh, that was close.
I think I've broken something.
Trust a Brandybuck and a Took!
What? That was just a detour.
A short cut.
- Short cut to what?
- Mushrooms!
That's mine.
That's nice, Merry.
Here's a nice one, Sam.
I think we should get off the road.
Get off the road!
Quick!
Be quiet!
What was that?
Anything?
Nothing.
What is going on?
That Black Rider was looking for something.
Or someone.
Frodo?
Get down!
I have to leave the Shire.
Sam and I must get to Bree.
Right.
Bucklebury Ferry. Follow me.
Run!
This way! Follow me!
Get the rope, Sam!
Frodo!
Run, Frodo!
Go!
- Hurry!
Frodo, come on!
- Come on! Faster!
- Jump!
- How far to the nearest crossing?
- The Brandywine Bridge. 20 miles.
Come on.
- What do you want?
- We're heading for the Prancing Pony.
Hobbits. Four hobbits!
What's more, out of the Shire by your talk.
What business brings you to Bree?
We wish to stay at the inn.
Our business is our own.
All right young sir, I meant no offense.
It's my job to ask questions after nightfall.
There's talk of strange folk abroad.
Can't be too careful.
Out of the way!
Watch where you're walking.
Excuse me.
Good evening, little masters.
What can I do for you?
If you're looking for accommodation, we got
some nice cozy hobbit-sized rooms available.
Always proud to cater to little folk, Mister...?
Underhill. My name's Underhill.
- Underhill, yeah.
- We're friends of Gandalf the Grey.
- Can you tell him we've arrived?
- Gandalf?
Gandalf.
Oh, yes...
...I remember. Elderly chap.
Big grey beard, pointy hat.
Not seen him for six months.
What do we do now?
Sam...
...he'll be here. He'll come.
Get out of my way!
What's that?
This, my friend, is a pint.
It comes in pints?
- I'm getting one.
- You got a whole half already!
That fellow's done nothing but
stare at you since we arrived.
Excuse me.
That man in the corner. Who is he?
He's one of them Rangers. They're dangerous
folk they are, wandering the wilds.
What his right name is, I've never heard,
but 'round here he's known as Strider.
Strider.
Baggins...
Baggins? Sure, I know a Baggins.
He's over there. Frodo Baggins.
He's my second cousin,
once removed on his mother's side...
...and my third cousin, twice removed....
- Pippin!
- Steady on, Frodo.
You cannot hide.
I see you.
There is no life...
...in the void.
Only...
...death.
You draw far too much attention
to yourself, "Mr. Underhill."
What do you want?
A little more caution from you.
That is no trinket you carry.
- I carry nothing.
- Indeed.
I can avoid being seen if I wish...
...but to disappear entirely, that is a rare gift.
- Who are you?
- Are you frightened?
Yes.
Not nearly frightened enough.
I know what hunts you.
Let him go!
Or I'll have you, Longshanks.
You have a stout heart, little hobbit.
But that will not save you.
You can no longer wait for the wizard, Frodo.
They're coming.
[Adûnaic] ♫ Bârî'n Katha-râd... ♫
[English] ♫ The Lords of the Eternal life... ♫
[Adûnaic] ♫ ...îdô Nidir... ♫
[English] ♫ ...now the Nine... ♫
[Adûnaic] ♫ ...nênâ-kham, nêpâm... ♫
[English] ♫ ...we come, we grasp... ♫
[Adûnaic] ♫ ...abarat aglar. ♫
[English] ♫ ...power and glory. ♫
What are they?
They were once men.
Great kings of men.
Then Sauron the Deceiver gave to them
nine rings of power.
Blinded by their greed,
they took them without question.
One by one, falling into darkness.
Now they are slaves to his will.
They are the Nazgûl.
Ringwraiths. Neither living nor dead.
At all times they feel...
... the presence of the ring...
...drawn to the power of the One.
They will never stop hunting you.
- Where are you taking us?
- Into the wild.
How can we know this Strider
is a friend of Gandalf?
I think a servant of the enemy would look fairer...
...and feel fouler.
- He's foul enough.
We have no choice but to trust him.
- But where is he leading us?
- To Rivendell, Master Gamgee.
- To the house of Elrond.
- Did you hear that? Rivendell.
We're going to see the elves.
- Gentlemen, we do not stop till nightfall.
- What about breakfast?
- You've already had it.
- We've had one, yes.
What about second breakfast?
Don't think he knows about second breakfast, Pip.
What about elevenses? Luncheon?
Afternoon tea? Dinner? Supper?
- He knows about them, doesn't he?
- I wouldn't count on it.
Pippin!
What do they eat when they can't get Hobbit?
[Sindarin] ♫  Tinúviel elvanui ...  ♫
[English] ♫ Tinúviel elven-fair ... ♫
"Tinúviel elvanui
(Tinúviel the elven-fair)
[Sindarin] ♫  ... elleth alfirin edhelhael ...  ♫
[English] ♫ ... immortal maiden elven-wise ... ♫
Elleth alfirin ethelhael
(Immortal maiden elven-wise)
O hon ring finnil fuinui
(About him cast her night-dark hair)
[Sindarin] ♫  ... o hon ring finnil fuinui ...  ♫
[English] ♫ ... about him cast her night-dark hair ... ♫
A renc gelebrin thiliol."
(And arms like silver glimmering.")
[Sindarin] ♫  ... a renc gelebrin.  ♫
[English] ♫ ... and arms like silver. ♫
Who is she?
This woman you sing of.
'Tis the Lay of Lúthien.
The elf-maiden who gave her
love to Beren, a mortal.
What happened to her?
She died.
Get some sleep, Frodo.
The power of Isengard is at your command...
... Sauron, Lord of the Earth.
Build me an army worthy of Mordor.
What orders from Mordor, my lord?
What does the Eye command?
We have work to do.
The trees are strong, my lord.
Their roots go deep.
Rip them all down.
This was the great watchtower of Amon Sûl.
We shall rest here tonight.
These are for you.
Keep them close.
I'm going to have a look around.
Stay here.
My tomato's burst.
Could I have some bacon?
Want a tomato, Sam?
- What are you doing?!
- Tomatoes, sausages, nice crispy bacon.
- We saved some for you, Mr. Frodo.
- Put it out, you fools!
- Put it out!
- That's nice! Ash on my tomatoes!
Go!
[Adûnaic] ♫ Bârî'n Katha-râd ♫
[English] ♫ The Lords of the Eternal life ♫
[Adûnaic] ♫ Îdô Nidir Nê ♫
[English] ♫ Now we Nine ♫
[Adûnaic] ♫ Nêbâ-bîtham ♫
[English] ♫ We deny ♫
[Adûnaic] ♫ Dir Nê Nâkham ♫
[English] ♫ We Nine approach ♫
[Adûnaic] ♫ Nêbâ-bîtham Ma-gâna-nanê ♫
[English] ♫ We renounce our Creator ♫
Back, you devils!
[Adûnaic] ♫ Nêtab~ Dâur~ ♫
[English] ♫ We cling to the darkness ♫
[Black Speech] Gûm-ishi...
[English] In the void...
[Black Speech] ...ashi...
[English] ...only...
[Black Speech] ...gurum!
[English] ...death!
Frodo!
Oh, Sam.
Strider!
- Help him, Strider.
- He's been stabbed by a Morgul blade.
This is beyond my skill to heal.
He needs elvish medicine.
Hurry!
We're six days from Rivendell!
He'll never make it!
Hold on, Frodo.
Gandalf!
[Quenya] ♫  I Cemen Nurrua ...  ♫
[English] ♫ The earth groans ... ♫
[Quenya] ♫  ... ar i súre...  ♫
[English] ♫ ... and the wind ... ♫
[Quenya] ♫  ... i sú-re ...  ♫
[English] ♫ ... the wind ... ♫
[Quenya] ♫  ... naina.  ♫
[English] ♫ ... is crying. ♫
... Gwaihir, go!
Look, Frodo. It's Mr. Bilbo's trolls.
Mr. Frodo? He's going cold.
Is he going to die?
He's passing into the shadow world.
He'll soon become a wraith like them.
- They're close.
- Sam, do you know the Athelas plant?
- Athelas?
- Kingsfoil.
Kingsfoil, aye, it's a weed.
It may help to slow the poisoning.
Hurry!
What's this, a ranger caught off his guard?
[Sindarin] ♫  Tinuviel elvanui ...  ♫
[English] ♫ Tinuviel the elven-fair ... ♫
Frodo.
[Sindarin] ♫  ... elleth alfirin.  ♫
[English] ♫ ... immortal maiden. ♫
[Sindarin] Im Arwen, Telin le thaed.
[English] I Arwen, I come to help you.
[Sindarin] Lasto beth nîn, tolo dan nan galad.
[English] Listen to my word, come back to the light.
Who is she?
Frodo.
- She's an elf.
- He's fading.
He's not going to last.
We must get him to my father.
- I've been looking for you for two days.
- Where are you taking him?
There are five wraiths behind you.
Where the other four are, I do not know.
[Sindarin] Dartho guin Beriain. Rych le ad tolthathon.
[English] Stay with the Hobbits. I will send horses for you.
[Sindarin] Hon mabathon! Rochon ellint im.
[English] I will take him! I am the swifter rider.
[Sindarin] Andelu i ven.
[English] The road is too dangerous.
What are they saying?
[Sindarin] Frodo fîr. Ae athradon i hîr ...
[English] Frodo is dying. If I cross the river ...
[Sindarin] ... tûr gwaith nîn beriatha hon.
[English] ... the power of my people will protect him.
I do not fear them.
[Sindarin] Be iest lîn.
[English] As you wish.
Arwen...
...ride hard. Don't Look back.
[Sindarin] Noro lim Asfaloth, noro lim!
[English] Ride fast Asfaloth, ride fast!
What are you doing?!
Those wraiths are still out there!
[Adûnaic] ♫  Bârî 'n Katharâd...  ♫
[English] ♫ Lords of the eternal life... ♫
[Adûnaic] ♫  ...îdô kham nêpâm.  ♫
[English] ♫ ...now approaching we grasp. ♫
[Sindarin] Noro lim Asfaloth!
[English] Ride fast Asfaloth!
[Adûnaic] ♫  Nênâkham, nêpâm...  ♫
[English] ♫ We approach, we grasp... ♫
[Adûnaic] ♫ ...abarat aglar. ♫
[English] ♫ ...power and glory. ♫
[Adûnaic] ♫  Nêpâm nêd aglar.  ♫
[English] ♫ We grasp for ourselves glory. ♫
[Adûnaic] ♫  Nidir, nêpâm.  ♫
[English] ♫ The Nine, we grasp. ♫
[Adûnaic] ♫  Nêpâm nêd aglar.  ♫
[English] ♫ We grasp for ourselves glory. ♫
Give up the halfling, She-elf.
If you want him, come and claim him.
[Sindarin] Nîn o Chithaeglir, lasto beth daer!
[English] Waters of the Misty Mountains, listen to the great word!
[Sindarin] Rimmo nîn Bruinen dan in Ulaer!
[English] Flow waters of Loudwater against the Ringwraiths!
[Sindarin] Nîn o Chithaeglir, lasto beth daer!
[English] Waters of the Misty Mountains, listen to the great word!
[Sindarin] Rimmo nîn Bruinen dan in Ulaer!
[English] Flow waters of Loudwater against the Ringwraiths!
[English] ♫ What Grace... ♫
No. No!
Frodo, no.
[English] ♫ ...is given me... ♫
Frodo, don't give in.
Not now.
[English] ♫ ...let it pass... ♫
What grace is given me...
...let it pass to him.
[English] ♫ ...to him. ♫
Let him be spared.
[English] ♫ Let him be spared. Mighty Valar, save him.  ♫
Save him.
[Sindarin] Lasto beth nîn. Tolo dan nan galad.
[English] Hear my voice. Come back to the light.
- Where am I?
- You are in the house of Elrond.
And it is 10 o'clock in the morning
on October 24th, if you want to know.
- Gandalf!
- Yes, I'm here.
And you're lucky to be here too.
A few more hours and you would
have been beyond our aid.
But you have some strength in you,
my dear Hobbit.
What happened, Gandalf?
- Why didn't you meet us?
- I am sorry, Frodo.
I was delayed.
A friendship with Saruman
is not lightly thrown aside.
One ill turn deserves another. It is over.
Embrace the power of the ring...
...or embrace your own destruction!
There is only one lord of the ring.
Only one who can bend it to his will.
And he does not share power.
So you have chosen...death.
Gandalf? What is it?
Nothing, Frodo.
Frodo!
- Sam.
- Bless you, you're awake!
Sam has hardly left your side.
We were that worried about you.
Weren't we, Mr. Gandalf?
By the skills of Lord Elrond,
you're beginning to mend.
Welcome to Rivendell, Frodo Baggins.
- Bilbo!
- Hello, Frodo, my lad.
Bilbo.
There and back again
A hobbit's Tale, by Bilbo Baggins.''
- This is wonderful.
- I meant to go back...
...wonder at the powers of Mirkwood...
...visit Lake-town...
...see the Lonely Mountain again.
But age, it seems, has finally caught up with me.
I miss the Shire.
I spent all my childhood pretending
I was off somewhere else.
Off with you, on one of your adventures.
But my own adventure turned out
to be quite different.
I'm not like you, Bilbo.
My dear boy.
- Now, what have I forgotten?
- Packed already?
No harm in being prepared.
- I thought you wanted to see the elves.
- I do.
- More than anything.
- I did.
It's just....
We did what Gandalf wanted, didn't we?
We got the ring this far, to Rivendell.
And I thought...
...seeing as how you're on the mend,
we'd be off soon.
Off home.
You are right, Sam.
We did what we set out to do.
The ring will be safe in Rivendell.
I am ready to go home.
His strength returns.
That wound will never fully heal.
He will carry it the rest of his life.
And yet to have come so far still bearing the ring...
...the Hobbit has shown extraordinary
resilience to its evil.
It is a burden he should never have had to bear.
- We can ask no more of Frodo.
- Gandalf, the enemy is moving.
Sauron's forces are massing in the East.
His eye is fixed on Rivendell.
And Saruman, you tell me, has betrayed us.
Our list of allies grows thin.
His treachery runs deeper than you know.
By foul craft, Saruman
has crossed orcs with goblin-men.
He's breeding an army in the caverns of Isengard.
An army that can move in sunlight
and cover great distance at speed.
Saruman is coming for the ring.
This evil cannot be concealed
by the power of the elves.
We do not have the strength to
fight both Mordor and Isengard!
Gandalf...
...the ring cannot stay here.
This peril belongs to all Middle-earth.
They must decide now how to end it.
The time of the elves is over.
My people are leaving these shores.
Who will you look to when we've gone?
The dwarves?
They hide in mountains seeking riches.
They care not for the troubles of others.
It is in men that we must place our hope.
Men?
Men are weak. The race of men is failing.
The blood of Numenor is all but spent,
its pride and dignity forgotten.
It is because of men the ring survives.
I was there, Gandalf.
I was there 3000 years ago...
... when Isildur took the ring.
I was there the day the strength of men failed.
Isildur, hurry! Follow me.
I led Isildur into the heart of Mount Doom...
...where the ring was forged,
the one place it could be destroyed.
Cast it into the fire!
- Destroy it!
- No.
Isildur!
It should have ended that day,
but evil was allowed to endure.
Isildur kept the ring.
The line of kings is broken.
There's no strength left in the world of men.
- They're scattered, divided, leaderless.
- There is one who could unite them.
One who could reclaim the throne of Gondor.
He turned from that path a long time ago.
He has chosen exile.
You are no elf.
Men of the South are welcome here.
- Who are you?
- I am a friend to Gandalf the Grey.
Then we are here on common purpose...
...friend.
The shards of Narsil.
The blade that cut the ring from Sauron's hand.
It's still sharp.
But no more than a broken heirloom.
Why do you fear the past?
You are Isildur's heir, not Isildur himseIf.
You are not bound to his fate.
The same blood flows in my veins.
The same weakness.
Your time will come.
You will face the same evil.
And you will defeat it.
[Sindarin] A si i-Dhúath ú-orthor, Aragorn.
[English] The shadow does not hold sway yet, Aragorn.
[Sindarin] Ú or le a ú or nin.
[English] Not over you, not over me.
[Sindarin] Renich i lú i erui govannem?
[English] Do you remember when we first met?
[Sindarin] Nauthannen i ned ôl reniannen.
[English] I thought I had strayed into a dream.
[Sindarin] Gwenwin in enninath.
[English] Long years have passed.
[Sindarin] Ú-'arnech in naeth i si celich.
[English] You did not wear the troubles you carry now.
[Sindarin] Renich i beth i pennen?
[English] Do you remember what I told you?
You said you'd bind yourself to me...
...forsaking the immortal life of your people.
And to that I hold.
I would rather share one lifetime with you...
...than face all the ages of this world alone.
I choose a mortal life.
- You cannot give me this.
- It is mine to give to whom I will...
...like my heart.
Strangers from distant lands, friends of old...
...you've been summoned here
to answer the threat of Mordor.
Middle-earth stands upon the brink of destruction.
None can escape it.
You will unite, or you will fall.
Each race is bound to this fate, this one doom.
Bring forth the ring, Frodo.
So it is true.
The ring of power...
The doom of men...
In a dream...
...I saw the eastern sky grow dark...
...but in the West a pale light lingered.
A voice was crying:
"Your doom is near at hand.
Isildur's bane is found."
(The Ring)
[Black Speech] Sherkuk-ishi
[English] In your blood
Isildur s bane.
Boromir!
(Gandalf)
[Black Speech] Ash nazg durbatulûk...
[English] One ring to rule them all...
(The Ring)
[Black Speech] Shre nazg golugranu kilmi-nudu...
[English] Three Rings for the Elven-kings under the sky...
(Gandalf)
[Black Speech] ...Ash nazg gimbatul...
[English] ...One ring to find them...
(The Ring)
[Black Speech] Ombi kuzd-durbagu... shirku
[English] Seven for the Dwarf-lords... blood
(Gandalf)
[Black Speech] ...Ash nazg thrakatulûk...
[English] ...One ring to bring them all...
(The Ring)
[Black Speech] Ash Burz-Durbagu burzum-ishi...
[English] One for the Dark lord on his dark throne...
(Gandalf)
[Black Speech] ...Agh burzum-ishi krimpatul.
[English] ...and in the darkness bind them.
Never before has any voice uttered the
words of that tongue here in Imladris.
I do not ask your pardon, Master Elrond...
...for the black speech of Mordor...
...may yet be heard...
...in every corner of the West!
The ring is altogether evil.
It is a gift.
A gift to the foes of Mordor.
Why not use this ring?
Long has my father, the Steward of Gondor...
...kept the forces of Mordor at bay.
By the blood of our people...
...are your lands kept safe.
Give Gondor the weapon of the enemy.
Let us use it against him.
You cannot wield it. None of us can.
The one ring answers to Sauron alone.
It has no other master.
And what would a ranger know of this matter?
This is no mere ranger.
He is Aragorn, son of Arathorn.
You owe him your allegiance.
Aragorn.
This is Isildur s heir?
And heir to the throne of Gondor.
[Sindarin] Havo dad, Legolas.
[English] Sit down, Legolas.
Gondor has no king.
Gondor needs no king.
Aragorn is right. We cannot use it.
You have only one choice.
The ring must be destroyed.
What are we waiting for?
[Black Speech] Daghburz-ishi makha, ghurarmu shirku.
[English] In the land of Mordor, a sacrifice of blood.
The ring cannot be destroyed, Gimli, son of Gloin...
...by any craft that we here possess.
The ring was made in the fires of Mount Doom.
Only there can it be unmade.
It must be taken deep into Mordor...
...and cast back into the fiery
chasm from whence it came.
[Black Speech] Makha gulshu darulu.
[English] Where the Shadows lie.
One of you...
...must do this.
One does not simply walk into Mordor.
Its black gates are guarded by more than just orcs.
There is evil there that does not sleep.
The great eye is ever-watchful.
It is a barren wasteland...
...riddled with fire, and ash and dust.
The very air you breathe is a poisonous fume.
Not with 10,000 men could you do this.
It is folly.
Have you heard nothing Lord Elrond has said?
The ring must be destroyed.
And I suppose you think you are the one to do it!
And if we fail, what then? What happens
when Sauron takes back what is his?
I will be dead before I see the
ring in the hands of an elf!
Never trust an elf!
Do you not understand? While you bicker
amongst yourselves, Sauron's power grows!
None can escape it!
You'll all be destroyed!
[Black Speech] Ash nazg durbatulûk...
[English] One ring to rule them all...
[Black Speech] ...Ash nazg gimbatul.
[English] ...One ring to find them.
[Black Speech] Ash nazg durbatulûk...
[English] One ring to rule them all...
[Black Speech] ...Ash nazg gimbatul.
[English] ...One ring to find them.
[Black Speech] Ash nazg durbatulûk...
[English] One ring to rule them all...
[Black Speech] ...Ash nazg gimbatul.
[English] ...One ring to find them.
[Black Speech] Ash nazg durbatulûk...
[English] One ring to rule them all...
I will take it.
I will take the ring to Mordor.
Though...
...I do not know the way.
I will help you bear this burden, Frodo Baggins...
...as long as it is yours to bear.
If by my life or death I can protect you...
...I will.
You have my sword.
And you have my bow.
And my ax.
You carry the fates of us all, little one.
If this is indeed the will of the Council...
...then Gondor will see it done.
- Mr. Frodo's not going anywhere without me.
- No indeed it is hardly possible to separate you...
...even when he is summoned to a
secret council and you are not.
Oy. We're coming too!
You'll have to send us home
tied up in a sack to stop us.
Anyway, you need people
of intelligence on this sort of...
...mission.
Quest.
Thing.
Well, that rules you out, Pip.
Nine companions.
So be it.
You shall be: The Fellowship of the Ring.
Great!
Where are we going?